Welcome back
today
Podcast style episode with Guillaume
who started out with minus two diopters spherical and minus two diopters cylinder, which is
unusually high cylinder and
situation where I usually say you've gotta probably take some time to sort that out. But Gilliaume has made kind of amazing progress
He's not wearing glasses and getting 20/25 vision during the day with largely no astigmatism
effects. A very interesting conversation we had; the audio unfortunately is
not completely fantastic. So hopefully you can bear with that.
It's a story. I really want to share and we couldn't address or fix the audio bit
So, hopefully this still works and here's Guillaume.
Ah, on peut parler français!
My French is terrible, but you know...
Ah it's just practice, eh?
A little bit. Alright Guillaume, if you want to introduce yourself and a little bit of background and where you started out with your myopia journey
Well, my name is Guillaume ..., I'm from ...
I started out with minus two diopters, both spherical and astigmatism
but I started my journey two years ago
by, uh, somebody suggested to just youtube some Chinese eye exercises which was obviously Bates method
Hey, I'm getting you sound a little bit like muffled you're not covering a microphone by any chance are you?
um, no, I don't think so. Does it sound better now?
It sounds it sounds like I can understand you but it's a little bit it has a little bit of this going on
it might be 'cause it's early morning and [laughs]
All right, nevermind, we'll make it work. So -2.5 yeah?
-2
both spherical and cylinder
Which is about, what, like a minus 3 in the spherical equivalent?
Right and
two years?
It's been, yeah it's been about two years, yup.
two years
Right. It's been a whole year since I've been in the endmyopia
the do it yourself, DIY
I really enjoyed it, I mean
When I started learning everything. I really stumbled upon it just from a youtube video.
I think it was probably an angry video
[both laughing]
And you're wearing no glasses right now, so you're where are you at today?
So, you know what, I see probably 20/25,
20/20 during the day
So I don't, I barely need to wear them
The only time I need to wear them is sometimes at night
Wow. And you're saying you had two diopters of astigmatism as well?
Yes, that's right. Now, my astigmatism,
or double vision, is not fully resolved and it's, and it's back and forth.
It happens more when I'm tired
at night. During the day, barely any.
And you know when I started my journey it was
At the time I, you know, I wasn't seeing the optometrist very often and
I basically
I did the Chinese eye exercises, which was basically Bates.
I had a slight improvement and then I plateaud and I didn't know what to do anymore.
But
I have to drink some water, Ithink my voice is ...
So basically,
I had noticed, however, that from wearing my old glasses
that sometimes when I was driving I was reading the signs kind of being clearer than other times.
Even though I was aware that my glasses were probably three or four years old,
the prescription, and I was out of date and I said well, maybe I should go see the optometrist
and I did go see the optometrist and
he prescribed; I was wearing -1.75
and same strength in astigmatism
and he prescribed the -2. He agreed,
he told me that the best thing was to have the optimal correction
And he wasn't happy that when I showed up I wasn't wearing my glasses
[both laughing]
That's
Not that unusual
So did you, did you do all the reductions by yourself or did you have; did you find somebody more supportive?
I did all the reductions except for the last one.
So basically, when he gave me the new prescription
I hesitated to fill it out because I didn't see the difference. He told me that I was still legal to drive with my previous prescription.
So I gave it some time and I kept doing the eye exercises
and you know, I got tired of having sore eyes from doing those eye exercises
So when I found, when I discovered endmyopia
well, the first thing was
I had seen a youtube video at the time probably around the same time I saw the optometrist
This was a few years ago.
The lady was basically saying that using reduced prescription
was a good way of reducing, and that she had found an optometrest to help her out
so that was my like next step, you know, like
From there on I was like, I'm not filling out my prescription.
You know, I'm gonna stay with my old prescription and
'cause it seemed to be still working fine.
but then I said, I'm gonna try to see if
I can find this video again and see if this lady has progressed.
And then I stumbled upon endmyopia on YouTube, probably saw Angie's video and
I just dove into it and then
The more I learned the more I was like, wow, ... an eye opener, you know, like literally
You know, I I started to do the; right away I stopped
using my distance vision to see up close and like
Now if I accidentally do it, I go, gosh, ...
You feel sick, right?
It's not meant for that.
And how fast did you reduce the cylinder? Like, two diopters is quite a lot and a lot of the time
it takes a good bit longer than a year to, to reduce even one diopter cylinder
so you really, from two diopters to nothing, that's a pretty significant reduction.
Well, well, that's just it. So that my; from the two diopter was really over prescribed
so I stuck to the 1.75 and then I reduced slowly
I mean, I don't recommend everybody doing this, but my, my old prescriptions were all pretty, pretty equalized.
Everything was equalized.
So I, what I started doing was I wore my, my differentials
which was my, my first prescription ever. I didn't know what it was. I thought it was like a -1.25
both spherical and cylinder.
However, I got it tested later when I, when I went through a holistic optometrist
which, which helped me.
She was actually pretty impressed with my eye exam.
And, I was able to tell her about endmyopia and
She encouraged the Bates method and I
She asked me what I was doing, and I told her what I was doing.
She was surprised because she used to do Bates method. She's teaching it too, right.
One thing that was interesting was during; my optometrist exam was, this was
maybe last March so a little less than a year ago
It had been four months into Endmyopia that I went to see my, the optometrist,
the holistic optometrist.
And when I was doing the eye exam the lights were on
She was ... making me look in a mirror
And she was telling me to look away look back, blink.
She's trying to help me, like, see better.
And I actually had active focus going at least once
where a line cleared up that I couldn't see before and I read it really fast. And she goes, "How did you do that?!"
Haha, she was impressed!
So I imagine next time I go to see her she's gonna be pretty impressed as well!
What, how many diopters was that with?
She, she gave me a spherical equivalent
so, ... she removed the complexity of my prescription, to get out the cylinder
Now the reason she did that
It wasn't fully clear,
even now. It was
To me looked a little blurry, but it wasn't too bad. Like it was it was a small challenge
because she gave me a, like, say a minus one
She gave me something with a slight astigmatism like a point twenty five astigmatism.
And it looked too perfect to me. I was like no, no, this this is good
I need to, I need to have a little bit more challenge here you know.
So she says okay, let me let me take it all out.
She took it all out and then just did a minus one point five spherical.
Which she told me was the spherical equivalent.
and
It worked out really great.
So there is, the way I reduced my astigmatism was because I was wearing my differentials
at work for the computer screen
which was a minus one
minus one spherical and cylinder and
Slowly I was ... basically bringing the screen back slowly slowly until
you know, to get the, the comfortable distance
and to always have a blur challenge, you know, blink and then clear it up
And you know, I spend most of my day on the computer
So that was; and I was sitting right beside a window, so I was able to look away and you know look back and
it was great, and then
What happened though, eventually, that when people were talking to me at my desk, that I would look up at them
My eyes would start to focus seeing through my differentials at them and start to get adapted to that
So the more and more clear it got around me
I was seeing more, starting to see more than sixty centimeters in front of me
I realized that my eyes were adapting to my, my old prescription.
So I decided to start,
I had another prescription that was in between
which was about a, it seems it was a 1.25
Yeah, well no it was a 1.5, both spherical and cylinder.
I would wear those ones for driving, which was a bit more of a challenge, but pretty good during the day.
Felt them a little strong then.
and then eventually I decided to just start using my differentials because I reduced so much and
started to wear my differentials all the time.
it was a bit of a challenge driving but things cleared up pretty quick; my eyes adapted pretty quick and
That was when within four months of beginning endmyopia, I decided to go see the holistic optometrist.
because I said, I can't be wearing my old glasses like that for too long. I need to reduce the correction...
I've had the minus, the -1.5 since.
Now,
I got to the point where you know I was following your guideline where inside with daylight
looking for 20/50 or 20/40 ... you know to, to know
works for the prescription, you know for the reduced prescription
But then I realized after a while that
that was my naked eye. I didn't need the glasses anymore.
I was seeing 20/50 20/40 without them, without the glasses during the day.
in the daytime
off the ... chart
So that's how ... for me. Then I keep making sure that
since, I just keep trying to make sure I don't do too many close-ups.
I, I find the more I like stare at my phone,
the worse my astigmatism gets, you know
Yeah, the phone, the phone distance and the size of that screen, like it's a tiny screen and you're in this tunnel
vision mode like really not ideal. And a lot of people say when you're when you're actively working on your vision and especially when
the glasses you're wearing or in your case, the glasses you're not wearing are like
You're at a challenge point already, any amount of phone, you really notice the difference
How did it change your, how much did that change your habits as far as your like phone time and screen time
since you were making all these improvements?
Well, it didn't change it too much,
except for the fact that I make sure to go outside and you know get the distance vision everyday
If I don't, then you know, it
It starts to get the spasm going right
So, I mean it's it's not super noticeable. But like in the morning, for example if I get out there
and I start, I start driving
I would do active focus at my first red light,
and then that would that would tell me how well I was seeing
at the sign, the first red light.
That would tell me how good I'm seeing for the day, see if I need to wear my glasses or not and
And the more the more I wake up, the more I do active focus the more it seems like once I'm fully awake,
I see, I see better. Right? So it's interesting.
And and you're saying how far do you get down on the chart now without any glasses?
Without any glasses on my ten foot chart, I can see the 20/25 very clear.
If I do some active focus, I start to see, I start to read the 20/20, and a little bit more.
Okay
Depending how bright it is.
Right, and that's indoor light, right?
Indoor light with the
I put the ... chart right now on the window.
The sun's not blaring straight in, but there's the daylight ... the background ...
That's pretty good. So how much do you end up wearing a glasses then generally?
Only when
It's like I said, I mean I try, you know what, at night time I started to not wear them
but it's
I can see where my blur horizon ends, you know like
yeah, so
It's, it depends on how, how bright it is and this and that, you know
Whether there's clouds in the sky and stuff, it really depends.
If I'm more tired too, I'm just not gonna take a chance and
I don't know if this is significant, I probably, I think I need to go probably get a
a reduced prescription again just for nighttime. I find my prescription's probably a little strong,
but with the astigmatism things, I mean I, I would like to have less astigmatism
I don't know how I would do. If I'm not wearing my glasses at night, the astigmatism's not that bad
When I put my glasses on, I still see like a line going through. So I have like 90 degree astigmatism
But during the day,
if it's poor indoor light. I used to have to wear them,
and now it's very rare.
Sometimes in like a, say like in a church or something, where it's
tends to be a bit dark and then I have a hard time seeing the screen
Depending on the day, I'll try to active focus and then sometimes it fully clears up,
sometimes it doesn't and the days it doesn't I probably wear my glasses.
Otherwise, I don't want to end up with eye strain, right?
One thing that was hard at the beginning was managing eye strain. Nowadays, eye strain is not an issue.
I know this because I'm used to it
And what, like what was the main motivation to get you into this whole thing
especially with the high, high cylinder, you're definitely working through some stuff
So there must have been some
Stronger than average reason for you to go through this experience
Well
you know, I
didn't get my glasses until tenth grade and
I hardly needed it.
So for me I, I started wearing it because people told me, you know, if you don't start wearing your glasses your eyes are gonna get worse
You know, I ended up partly listening to it. I wore them for about ten years
And I was just getting sick of it, you know, like
Like up to 16 with no glasses and then
I get my first prescription and then I don't start wearing them until, like regularly, until I'm about 21, you know.
And then
So it was really more than that, probably eleven years or so.
But, you know I get sick of it, always having to be behind your lenses, and the glasses are always dirty, and then you break your glasses.
You know taking them off and trying to see
You know
My spherical equivalent was like a minus 3, right. So looking around everything was a little bit too blurry
You know like, I could see and if I start; I remember if I start
... whenever I go camping and stuff, I wouldn't wear them.
And I noticed that it was actually improving.
To a certain point, but then when I get back to the city I'd start wearing them again, you know
... if I was driving I'd wear them.
and
But just the very fact that I saw
the first initial improvements
or I sort of discovered active focus back when I first all started this and I was wearing my reduced prescription
and things were showing up on the street signs with my old prescription,
I thought yeah, you know what?
There's gotta be a way
And it was just very exciting to discover all this information that you provided
... even more ...
So you found, you found us from the YouTube channel?
Yup, on the YouTube, yup.
Aw man.
Its so, I still, I can't see my face on these videos. I can never rewatch these videos
I can't listen to my voice, it's such a horribly cringy thing,
but so many people are like, I found you from the YouTube channel, and like every time I'm dreaming about
turning that thing off with me talking
...like you come around and you're like, that's how I found it.
It's like, aw crap.
So, that's awesome, is there any particular like
If you, if you look at the whole thing
Like is there any particular revelation or,
or message or something that you you'd share with others or even with like
yourself before you found this whole idea about the difference between
living with glasses and going through all this trouble to get rid of them?
Well, I mean, it's, it's good to know the truth, right?
...you get to know the truth, ..., right?
[ laughs ]
...
Who wants to be stuck behind lenses, when you don't have to, right?
Yeah, and you started late, so I think it's easier; the later you start the more like you remember life without glasses the easier
I think it is to make that, make that transition back
Yeah
Well, super cool like I'm really, I
it's kind of cherry picking I have to admit it, but I really like that part of the story like when you go from
glasses to not needing glasses or not needing glasses more of the time so I'm
I'm super glad that you took the time to share and come on and, and have this conversation because
it's, it's the most exciting part. Like all the reductions of course are super important and interesting and all that but like
Going from wearing those things and not wearing those things is like the juiciest part
Mm hm.
And then, one thing I noticed ... when I
when I was like ... in daytime
when I tried to wear my normalized
sometimes it was a bit too strong, and that's when I
...like, no I think that prescription is too strong
And that's when I switched to my differentials so I could see during the day because my
my normalized vision ...
... could tell right away it was too strong ...
Yeah, and that on the side note and you know all this but just in case, people that are listening or watching; it's perfectly fine
to
wear some correction when you need it. Because part of the benefit is you keep your visual cortex in this space where it
expects a certain amount of clarity. Right, like you have this, I call it like the reference clarity, where you're like
your brain is like, oh this is what the world should look like, and
having that especially in this last, bit like when you're around that last dioptre is super helpful because
When you wear them when you need them, you have that clarity. You're not getting used to blur, like you're not getting
quote-unquote lazy. And then when you take the glasses off
it's much easier to stay in an active focus mode and in a challenge mode to maintain, to get to that same level.
So it's totally fine to wear them when you feel like otherwise you're not, not trying.
No rush. No rush, 'cause
One of the things ... that gave me a bit of a incentive to improve my eyesight,
was my step-mother also improved her eyesight
And her it was, she had like a ...
And she moved into a place where it's like twelve stories up, condo that has a beautiful view.
And her eyes adapted to that long distance view
to the point were when I started my journey, I was telling her what I was learning
and she actually improved faster than me
She saw just a regular optometrist and
she ended up ... glasses. She's given like a .75
She was telling me, do you think I should fill the prescription?
I said you see fine, you don't need it any more,
your eyes adapted to that long distance
she
She was able to go to the Ministry of Transportation and remove the x from her license.
She passed the eye test with flying colours.
When I saw that she; she had started to get ... improvement just from adapting to the, to her, to the new scenery
The eyes are adapting, right?
And said, well if that's the case then I can certainly train, start to train my distance vision.
I noticed when I was young; I remember when I was young that I
I didn't develop much of my distance vision.
I would walk down the street and I would mostly look on the ground instead of looking straight up, you know
but for myself
if it seems like it's never too late to train your distance vision, so
... give it a shot!
Your, yeah and you make great progress. That's so awesome
And I personally, really appreciate it because it, I think it adds a lot. Like us having this conversation is so much more than just
words on the screen and improvement reports and Facebook stuff like
Actually, right like, people can see your face and that there's a big difference I think and going. Ok. I don't need these things
so much anymore. So I really appreciate you taking the time and coming on and sharing.
So I did a test with, with my neighbourhood kids.
And I brought them in and I had them look at my 20-foot eye chart.
Actually, the, the 10-foot one, mostly
and this was in winter
and
During the daylight, you know indoor, well-lit
and most of them could see up to 20/40, 20/50.
So I said, why don't you go in my window and start looking at the branch in the trees?
For about five minutes, and blink couple times.
And they would come back to my eye chart and they would read an extra line every time.
So ... down to about twenty, 20/25 or 20/20, doing that a couple times.
So I thought that was really neat.
And that's exactly what happens, right? And like I bet they spent too much time on their phones and then they go to the optometrist
And the optometrist at that point, they get them for that first, right like around one diopter, and then they're wearing glasses.
Yeah, exactly.
Yeah, that's rough. That's rough. If there's nobody there to tell them that like, this is how people become quote-unquote myopes, right.
Mm hm, exactly.
My optometrist was, was surprised that my first prescription actually had astigmatism in it.
Usually, I'm not sure usually I think they don't usually do that, first prescriptions, but
But, can't wait 'til I have like, no more astigmatism, like what,
What would your advice be
towards that? Like, because I mean
From what I've read from you is ..., try to clear up like, just by staring.
And it does work. It does work.
I think sometimes, sometimes, I remember sometimes I see like
you know, double, triple moons. Well double moons, you know?
[laughs]
But,
It, you don't, like general, okay.
So, astigmatism has a little bit more variance than myopia
because myopia generally just, ciliary spasm and lens-induced myopia. So the axial length.
So it's fairly predictable whereas with astigmatism
that's not always the case, right? Like the corneal surface might be shaped funny.
You can get a test for that. There's some astigmatism that's genetic. So there is not really a
one-size-fits-all answer
In cases where the astigmatism is two-diopter and over,
I'm always a little bit more cautious.
Like, it tends to take a longer amount of time like
Diopter; One diopter and under, a lot of times you can just get rid of it.
Like, between a one and two diopters, there's a much more gray area as to how long it might take
and you can't really active focus your way out of that directional blur or the double vision.
So you need more of a:
You're staring at the double moon, and you wait for,
you're not blinking. You're not doing anything. You're just waiting.
You start to see the double moon moving around.
And that's your visual cortex going, "How do I make this work?"
Right? And it keeps realigning and realigning and eventually it might just be one moon, for a moment.
And it might not work every time, right?
And you might find that it works better with things like the moon, actually things that are lit, right, where there's more
contrast between the foreground and the, the background.
But that kind of activity takes time.
Like you're doing the right thing. Like you want to reduce the, the astigmatism correction to where you have some of that,
and you can add a little bit of spherical to reduce some of that effect,
but the ideal scenario is that you have a little bit of it.
Not so much that it's bothersome,
but also not none.
And then, when you feel in that kind of mood, just find something that gives you that double image
and then just keep looking at it, and give your brain time to try to figure out how to align.
Yeah, and then and then just be patient.
You know what I mean? There's that middle ground between,
between not having enough challenge or not challenging yourself enough, and overdoing it.
Right? Like because it's not going to change that much faster if you put in a whole lot more effort
It's just a little bit consistently, you know what I mean?
Like, the more regularly you do a little bit of challenge,
that's much more effective than, like
If you'd asked me about this beforehand, I would have said don't take out all the astigmatism.
Seems to work for you
so that's perfectly fine,
but the, recognizing how much of this is uncomfortable
versus how much of this do I need to give my brain a target to work out that double vision image
... Sometimes when I ... stare at the screen ...
I get part,
like, half of it is blurry,
but then I could see before it and I could see after it
... then after staring at it,
it clears up ...
And then I remember when I first started to ... my glasses
and go for a walk during the daylight
And I would look at the street, like, the house numbers
And it was, it was interesting.
It was like, I could see some blur but I could also see.
I'd focus, focus on things, things were starting to show up
and I remember even just going to the grocery store
oh my goodness
even with my differentials, eh?
Go to the grocery store and I'd tried looking all around, look at all the items
and it was like, it was like a discovery, you know, it's like,
It's like trying, it's like shining a flashlight in the light and you only see so far, you know?
Can only so much when you understand that blur horizon, you know?
Yeah, but now you're okay, right? More or less.
Oh yeah, now ...
it's, it's interesting, the process ...
You see a up to a ..., and ... see more and more and more
Well that's kind of, that's kind of what my challenge is that night now
because I, you know, I can see a certain amount, and then if it's uncomfortable I have to wear my glasses
i don't like taking too many risks, especially at night, but
I figure I need to adapt to ... night seeing as well, right?
Without getting blur-adapted.
Yeah, that's the fine line, right? Like, as long as you're not accepting blur and as long as you're, the challenges are right, that's fine
Mm hm
Well, I really appreciate it. Thanks for getting up early, or maybe you get up early anyway, but
I appreciate you being on here this early to share your progress.
Not a problem, my pleasure.
All right, so that was our episode with Guillaume
with the audio that was not amazing, but
minus two diopters of spherical gone
Largely gone or reduced to a point where he doesn't really need glasses when, especially in the daytime. And two diopters of cylinder
which normally would be a
significant impediment to making this kind of improvement very quickly.
Also to a point where usably he doesn't need them. So that's really fantastic.
If you want me to find more of these we have lots and lots and lots,
thousands of emails of improvement reports. I can ask more people to participate in these kinds of chats.
I'm happy to do it. If you think it's useful feel free to leave comments below. Leave a like if you find these
useful and then I will see you in the next one.